<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Browser Cache | Segundamano's Backstage]]></title>
  <link href="http://backstage.segundamano.mx/blog/categories/browser-cache/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://backstage.segundamano.mx/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-16T13:16:34-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://backstage.segundamano.mx/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Segundamano.mx Tech Team]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static Assets Cache Busting]]></title>
    <link href="http://backstage.segundamano.mx/blog/2016/01/15/static-assets-cache-busting/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-15T17:36:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://backstage.segundamano.mx/blog/2016/01/15/static-assets-cache-busting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>TL;DR</h2>

<p>You want to set up cache headers with an expiration time in the far future, but
be able to force the browser to download the new version of an updated file. You
should use file content&rsquo;s fingerprinting as a filename part.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s cache busting and why it&rsquo;s useful</h2>

<p>So, you&rsquo;re worried about the performance of your site and have leveraged cache
headers, which tell the browser to hang onto the cached files for a given amount
of time, commonly this time is as long as six months or more, or maybe you&rsquo;re
even using a CDN for all your static assets: images, CSS and JavaScript files.</p>

<p>Then, during the next release of your site you realize something is wrong, there
is a bug and you have already spent some time looking for the cause, only to
discover that a CSS file seems not to have the last changes introduced by the last
deploy, so you empty your browser cache, reload, and voilá, issue solved.</p>

<p>When using a CDN it&rsquo;s a little bit harder to debug this kind of problems, you will
have to check whether the asset is being served by your upstream server or by your
CDN, if so, you will have to purge your CDN caching, too.</p>

<p>You need a way for breaking the cache and force the browser to download a new copy
of the CSS file every time it has changes, without having to empty the browser cache
or purging your CDN. Enter cache busting.</p>

<h2>Cache busting using query strings</h2>

<p>This technique uses a query string appended to the resource link, it could be
whatever you want, but timestamps and version numbers are suggested.</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="css/example.css?v1.0" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>One downside for this approach is that sometimes query strings are ignored as a part
of the filename, for the browser that means the file hasn&rsquo;t changed, and the cache
busting doesn&rsquo;t happen.</p>

<h2>Cache busting by file fingerprinting</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s another technique which modifies the filename using a hash (MD5, SHA1,
etc.), this hash is commonly placed before the file extension, using it as a part
of the filename allows to effectively break the browser cache and download the new
version.</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="css/example.bc67fbd9.css" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The hash is computed based on the content of the file, so that it changes whenever
a file is updated, it doesn&rsquo;t change otherwise. The hash is also computed one file at
a time, that is, each file has a unique hash.</p>

<h3>Do it automatically</h3>

<p>Computing the hash and renaming the files manually is error prone and you shouldn&rsquo;t
do this. The only way for this to work, is to add this process into the build stage,
so the source files are in the <code>src/</code> directory, with their names unmodified and then
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/hashmark">process them</a> and output the final files in
the <code>build/</code> directory, with their names containing the hash.</p>

<p>But, what about all the references to these files? These references must be
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/map-replace">updated</a> on the build stage, too, otherwise
the CSS, HTML or JavaScript files using any of these assets would be using an outdated
version of them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
